Welcome to the wild world of AI, where
if you blink, you'll miss a dozen
updates and maybe even lose your side
hustle as grandma's go-to geek squad.
For beginners, it feels like trying to
hop on a train already speeding at 1,000
mph. So, today I'm hitting the brakes
and giving you the ultimate beginner's
guide to chat GPT, and we're going to
discuss how to actually use it without
accidentally proposing to it. So, let's
get into it. Let's start by breaking
down the various pricing tiers so you
know which plan is best for you. Now,
there's a total of five different plans.
You've got free, plus pro, business, and
chatgpt enterprise. For most people,
you're just going to either want the
free plan or the plus plan, unless you
use AI a ton or you have very specific
business needs that only the business
plan has. On the free plan, you do get
access to GPT5. However, they only allow
you to have 10 messages per 5 hours on
the free plan. And then after you've
used your 10 messages, you can still
chat with it. It just lowers you down to
a faster but kind of dumber model. On
the free plan, you can also use GPT5's
thinking capabilities for tougher
prompts, but you only can do it once per
day on the free model. If you want to
generate videos or images, well, the
free plan will generate a limited amount
of images per day on a sort of slower
image generation model. And the free
plan does not have access to Sora for
video generation. Now, if you upgrade to
the plus plan, the $20 per month plan,
once again, you get access to GPT5 and
you get 160 messages every 4 hours,
which for the majority of people will be
absolutely plenty. You also can use the
advanced thinking GPT5 on this one, and
instead of just once a day like you get
on the free plan, you get 3,000 per
week. You also get a better, faster
image generator. You get access to Sora
video generation. Although, if you have
Sora on the plus plan, you can generate
5 seconds at 720p or 10 seconds at the
lower resolution of 480p. So, you don't
get the best Sora video generation model
on the plus plan. You also get access to
codeex, which is their sort of coding
platform, and agent mode, which will
actually use a browser on your behalf.
It does say the plus plan includes
projects, but projects are now also
available on the free plan. They just
haven't updated this page yet. And then
if you want to shell out 200 bucks per
month, you get GPT5, unlimited access to
all the GPT5 models, including their
best thinking model, which isn't even
available inside of Plus, unlimited
faster image creation, a better version
of Sora video, which will actually
generate up to 20 seconds at 1080p, and
they won't have a watermark on them. And
again, access to the agent mode, the
codeex agent and any new features that
they roll out typically roll out into
the pro plan first before eventually
going into the plus plan and then
finally going into the free plan. So,
the higher the tier you pay for, the
quicker the access you get to new
features. Again, I would say for the
majority of the world, you're going to
be fine on the free plan. And if you do
find yourself hitting limits where the
amount of messages it gives you isn't
quite enough, then the $20 per month is
going to be probably the best for
everybody. And very, very few people,
unless you're a power user of AI like I
am, and some of the other YouTubers that
talk about AI, you probably don't
actually need the $200 a month plan. Get
started on the free plan. If you hit
limitations, then consider upgrading.
That would be my advice. All right. Now,
let's dial in our chat GPT account. To
start, I'm actually logged in on a free
account. So, what you're seeing right
now is a completely free account. You
can see down in the bottom left here,
the most common question that OpenAI
gets, their number one question that
they get to their technical support or
wherever is all about privacy controls.
How do I make sure whatever I'm saying
doesn't actually get sent off to OpenAI?
And since that's the number one most
asked question, let's talk about that
first. If you click on your name down in
the bottom left here and I click on
settings and then I click on data
controls here, you can see that you have
the option to improve the models for
everyone. And it's turned on by default.
If I turn this off, improve the model
for everyone. You can see that what this
is doing is it's no longer allowing my
content to be used to train the models.
So again, if you want to make sure your
data doesn't go back to chat GPT to
train the models, you can turn this off.
Now, I'm a power user. I give a lot of
feedback to them. So, I like to leave it
on. I have no problem with what I'm
putting into the chat box making its way
back to OpenAI. If you ever want to
completely close your ChatgPT account
and not use it anymore, they do have an
option to export your data, which will
export all of your past chats, so you
have logs and records of all the chats
that you've had with them. Then you can
delete all your chats if you want, and
then you can go to the account page and
delete your account. So, that option is
always available to you. Now, if there's
just specific chats that you want to
make sure they don't get back in the
training data, it doesn't save it in
your chat history. It's basically an
incognito window for your chats, you can
click on this button up in the top right
called temporary chat. If I turn this
on, you can see that our chat will not
go into history. It won't help train
their models, and it won't save anything
we say into chat GPT's memory to pull up
later in future discussions. So nothing
is getting saved here. That's the option
if you don't want to turn it off across
the board, but just on specific chats.
You just turn on temporary chat, aka
chat GPT's incognito mode. While you're
getting your account set up, you can
also give it some custom instructions to
better tailor it to respond how you'd
want it to respond. So again, if I come
down to the bottom here, click on my
name, there's a button that says
customize chat GPT. If I click customize
chat GPT, we can give it a bunch of
instructions on how we want chat GPT to
respond to us. We can tell it what name
we want it to call you. So mine, you'll
notice it always says, "Hey, Matt," or
"Matt is always in the reply." That's
because I told it what to call me. It
asks, "What do you do?" So I would put,
you know, I'm a YouTuber. I'm a teacher.
I'm a whatever role you play. You'd put
it here. So it has that context. You
have the option to change the
personality to a cynic, a robot, a
listener, or a nerd. I just keep it on
default, but feel free to play with
these and see if you like the way it
responds a little better. Now, this is
what I think is really valuable here is
what traits should chat GPT have. So, I
just jumped over to my main account here
so I can show you how I have a lot of
these settings set up. Here's what I
described. I said, "Skip the formalities
about being an AI chat model. Address me
as Matt. When a long explanation is
required, give me long explanations. If
a really short and concise answer will
do, I prefer that." So, I'm telling it,
only give me long answers if you need
to. And then, since I'm a YouTuber and I
ask a lot of questions about titles and
thumbnails and things, I gave it the
extra context. If I ever ask for ideas
for YouTube titles, be sure to suggest
only titles that are 50 characters or
less. So, now when I'm brainstorming
YouTube titles, it only suggests titles
that are 50 characters or less, no
matter what, because it knows this
inside of the custom instructions. And
then down here, it says, "Anything else
chat GPT should know about you?" and I
gave it some extra details that could
help inform the decisions when it's
giving me replies. So imagine these
things are going into every single
prompt that you give chat GPT. So if you
just ask like a one-s sentence question
to chat GPT, it'll ask that question,
but then also feed it this information
and this information. And if any of it's
relevant, we'll also use that
information in your prompt. So down here
I gave it details like I'm based in San
Diego, full-time YouTuber, make my money
through AdSense and sponsorships and you
know some of the focuses I have around
my channel and just some additional
context about me that ChatGpt might find
helpful for the various questions I ask
it. Definitely fill out this as early as
you can to make sure that you design and
tailor chat GPT to be what you want it
to be. And then down under advanced, you
have the option to turn on some chat GPT
capabilities. If they're not on already,
I would turn them all on. Web search is
probably going to be the one you use the
most. And if you do a lot of vibe coding
and stuff like that, well, you can write
code in here. You'll want the advanced
voice on as well. If you ever decide to
use the voice mode and chat with it and
canvas, we'll get to in a minute, but
it's like a editor sort of inside of
chat GPT. I would just turn them all on.
While we're dialing this all in and
getting it to be the chat GPT we want it
to be, I would also go into the settings
here and go to personalization and make
sure that referenced save memories is on
and referenced chat history is on. Now,
you don't have to do this, but I find
this to be really really beneficial
because it uses past conversations
you've had with chat GPT for context of
your current conversations. And I found
this really helpful for things like
let's say I am using chat GPT to give me
fitness advice. Well, it knows what
workout routine it recommended to me
yesterday. So when I ask it again today,
it's not going to recommend the same
workout routine because it knew what it
recommended yesterday. So things like
that I find really helpful. Now if it
remembers things that you're like, man,
I wish you did not remember that like
remove that from my chat GPT. You can
actually manage the memories. if you
click in here and all of the memories
that it's saved about you are in here
and you can go ahead and delete any of
those memories or clear them all if you
want. Now, if you have one of the paid
plans, you'll see this check box here.
This isn't going to be available on the
free model. But if you are on the 20 or
$200 month model, you will see this. And
I recommend turning this on. If this is
off, up at the top, my chat GBT5
dropdown will show some models. It'll
have the instant model, a thinking
model, and a pro model. And then under
legacy models, you'll be able to select
GPT40. But if you do want to play around
with additional models and see if maybe
there's a model that you prefer better
over the default, turning on show
additional models inside of the general
tab inside of your settings will give
you quite a bit more models to play
with. So you have 40, 4.1, 4.5, 03, 04
mini, and more here. Now, I am on the
pro plan, the $200 a month plan. So, I'm
probably seeing more models here than
you'll see on the $20 a month plan, but
if there's some models that aren't
showing, turn on that switch and it will
update it to give you access to even
more models. Inside the settings, you
also have access to connectors to
connect to things like GitHub, Gmail,
Google Calendar, Google Drive, Dropbox,
Canva, all these things. To be honest, I
don't use the connectors very often. you
might find them helpful, something to
play with. They haven't been extremely
useful for me, but it is connected to my
Google calendar and my email and things
like that. So, I can ask it questions
about are there any important emails I
need to focus on right now or how busy
is my schedule next week. Now, I can ask
it this question, but I do need to make
sure that if I do ask it a question like
this, I turn on the connector by
clicking on the plus, going to use
connectors, and then under sources, you
have options for your various
connectors. So, it does search Google
Calendar automatically. But if you're
trying to get it to search GitHub or
Google Drive or something like that, you
will need to switch it on. Have you ever
felt like your marketing playbook
stopped working overnight? Traffic's
down, AI is rewriting the rules, and
you're stuck guessing which prompts,
messages, and channels will actually
move the needle. It's frustrating, and
it wastes time and budget. That's why I
partnered with HubSpot to share their
loop marketing prompt library. It's 100
engineered AI prompts built for the way
growth really works now, across four
stages: Express, tailor, amplify, and
evolve. You'll get battle tested prompts
like a brand differentiation analyzer to
nail your positioning, a competitor
gapfinder to uncover angles you can own,
a customer journey mapper to fix drop
offs, and an intent signal identifier to
spot ready to buy moments. No more
generic chat prompts. This is structured
step-by-step guidance so you can drop
straight into your workflow. If you want
to stop guessing and start shipping
smarter experiments that compound, grab
the loop prompt library through the link
in the description. It's free and it'll
make your next campaign measurably
better. Thanks so much to HubSpot for
sponsoring today's video. Now, let's get
back to it. All right, now that you've
picked your pricing model and you've got
all of your settings dialed in so that
ChatGpt performs the way you want it to,
let's go over some more prompting tips
to get the best out of Chat GPT. Tip
number one, make sure you're using the
right model for the job. If it's a real
simple question to answer and doesn't
really need to think through math or
logic, just use the auto selector or the
instant answer where it gives you an
answer right away. If it's a more
complex problem that might require math
or logic, then use one of the thinking
models. Now, this is inside the paid
plan. If you're in the free plan and you
want to use the thinking model, you'll
notice that you don't have the same
options up here on the free plan. So
instead, you do it by clicking on this
plus and clicking on think longer. With
this think longer selected, you'll be
using the thinking model. But remember,
you do have a limit to how often you can
use the thinking model on the free plan.
So, if I give a prompt like solve this
step by step, if a train leaves at 9:15
going 65 mph and another leaves at 10
a.m. going 80 mph, when will they meet
if the first has a 45minute head start?
They're both headed in the same
direction with the same end destination.
Assume they are on track side by side.
Now, if I use the instant model here,
the very fast model, and submit this, we
can see that it worked through the math
and eventually came up with the answer.
They'll meet each other at 115. Now, I
don't know if that's the correct answer
or not, but it did this really, really
fast and didn't think too hard about it.
Now, if I paste in this same prompt, but
this time switch it to the thinking
model and submit it, we'll see that it
actually takes time to really think it
through. It thought for a little bit
longer and did come up with the same
answer. So, I guess this question wasn't
too complex of a question for it to
figure out. Just keep in mind that if
there's a lot of math or logic involved,
turn on thinking. If it's an easy
question that doesn't require math or
logic, you won't need thinking. It's
probably not going to benefit you too
much. Tip number two, use the projects.
Projects are amazing. These are like
folders that organize various chats
together. If I come over here and click
on new project, I could give it a name.
Let's just call this one demo project.
And then create the project. Once you've
created a project, you can add files to
this project. So you can drag and drop
text files or images or PDFs or whatever
into the project files and then every
chat that you have inside of this
project is going to use that information
while you're chatting with it. But what
I really like these projects for is that
you can give custom instructions for
every single project that are
individualized to that project. So if I
click the three dots in the top right,
click on add instructions, I can give
custom instructions that only happen
during this project. So, for example, if
I want to build a health coach, I can
put a bunch of information in here
telling it that it's a health coach and
that every prompt I give it is going to
be related to health and that it should
follow instructions related to that.
Another new thing that they just sort of
sneakily rolled out and didn't really
make any sort of announcement about is
the fact that you can have memory that
just lives in one of those projects. So
again, if I click new project, I'm just
going to call this one test project. And
then click on the little gear icon under
memory, you have the option for default
project can access memories from outside
of the chats. So it will access memory
from any of my other projects, any of my
chats, or you can set project only
memory. So it will only remember past
chats that you had within just that
project. And this is really really
powerful because it will make it so you
have like your own separate individual
chat GPT area for a single topic that
doesn't listen to any of the noise of
the other chats you're having. Really,
really powerful. I wish they made it so
you could turn it on after you've
already built the project, but once you
save the project, you are locked into
whatever option you set here. So, some
of my old projects where I wish it had
project only memory, I don't have it
turned on because it wasn't available
when I built those projects,
unfortunately. But here's an example of
a project that I've created. And as you
can see, I use quite often. You'll
notice there's one file in here that I
uploaded. I don't believe I can open
this file and show it to you, but what
is in this file is information on my
health. I gave it information about the
supplements I take every morning. I gave
it information about my diet. I gave it
information about my height and weight,
my age. I gave it details about my
lifestyle, what exercises I like doing,
which ones I don't like doing, and I
just dumped a bunch of information into
a text file so it can use that as
context of my discussions and kind of
know about me. And then up here, I did
set custom instructions as well. You are
a personal health coach. User will share
progress reports and keep the custom
instructions with the latest relevant
info to the health journey. You will
help with crafting custom meal plans,
custom workout routines, supplement
stacks, etc., etc. And then I actually
plugged in some more details. My name is
Matt. I often feel too busy to work out
or cook meals, etc. So, I gave it custom
instructions on what this project should
be. And now, whenever I chat inside of
this health coach project, it knows all
about my personal health information
because of the file I uploaded. and it
knows how to respond because of the
custom instructions telling it that it's
a health coach that helps me with what
my next steps on my health journey are.
So, projects super powerful. I've
started building out projects for almost
every discussion I have. I have a health
coach. I have a journal where I journal
directly in here and then it gives me
feedback on my journal. I've got an
investment advisor where I ask it for
advice on various investments I'm
thinking about making. I do a lot of
sponsorships for HubSpot. I've got one
that actually writes the integrations
for me. I've got one that writes short
scripts. I've built out tons of projects
and I use them all all the time. Most of
the time if I'm chatting, I'm chatting
within a project and not just by
clicking new chat up here because it's
sort of bundling things for me in a nice
tidy area. And this projects used to be
only on the paid plans, but the projects
is now a free feature as well. So even
if you're on a free plan, you have the
ability to use projects. Probably one of
the most powerful but underrated
features of chat GPT in my opinion is
projects. Use them. They're really cool.
Tip number three, just use natural
language and talk to it like you're
messaging somebody on Slack. I think a
lot of people try to over complicate and
prompt engineer when you don't really
need to. For most cases, just asking for
help like you would ask a friend for
help over a text message works just
fine. Example, I've got 2 hours to cook
dinner tonight. What's something simple
but impressive I could make for my
family? It gave me a few good options
and I'm ready to cook. Tip number four,
ask direct questions, not vague
questions. So, instead of a prompt like,
"Tell me something about baking," you'll
get a much better result out of a prompt
like, "What are the five key steps to
baking a sourdough loaf at home?" This
is clearly going to get you much closer
to the outcome you actually want. Tip
number five, be specific and give
context. Sometimes you can just put this
in the custom instructions so it does
this every time. But if you want just
this specific chat to focus on a
specific area, think about the role of
the chatbot, the audience the chatbot is
speaking back to, the length you want,
the style you want it to respond in, and
do and don'ts of how you want the output
to be. You don't have to plug all of
those in every single time you prompt,
but the more detail you can give, the
better the response you're going to get.
A good example, act like a travel guide.
Plan a 3-day New York trip for a family
with kids under 10. We don't want
museums, but love parks, food, and
quirky activities. Show it in a table by
day. So, we're even giving the output
style. And just like that, it gives us
an output in a table format that
includes the additional criteria that we
gave it. Tip number six is along the
same lines. Tell it what format you want
the output to be in. So, maybe you want
a table or a bulleted list or maybe you
want JSON. It can do any of that. You
just need to tell it to. So, for
example, make me a workout plan in a
table with columns for day, workout
sets, reps, and notes. It'll give me a
table back in that same format. And then
I could say if I want, convert this to
JSON for me. And we can see it will
write the same content, but in a JSON
format. Tip number seven, give it both
good and bad examples of what you want
the output to be. Doing this will ensure
that it knows exactly what you're
looking for and that it's not going to
give you some vague response that you
didn't ask for. Here's an example.
You're my copy coach. I want five hooks
that follow this good style and avoid
the bad style. Good. I asked three AIs
the same question. Only one got it
right. And here's the reason why this is
good. It's got a clear tease with
stakes. Bad AI is interesting and
changing everything. It's very vague and
very low stakes. Now write five hooks
for a video on GPT5 hidden features
matching good and avoiding bad. So we're
telling it what we want as well as what
we don't want. And it gives us five
decent hooks that follow our good style
and avoid the bad style. Tip number
eight, don't assume that chat GPT's
first try is the best it can do. For
example, I gave it a prompt to write me
a 60-second YouTube intro script about
AI in schools. It wrote me this script,
but maybe I'm not super happy with this
script. Well, Chad GPT is very good at
iterating off of what it just built. So,
I can give it a prompt like tighten it
so it feels more energetic, less formal,
and under a hundred words. It will take
this original script here and make the
tweaks that I asked it to make in my new
script. So, keep iterating after your
first prompt. Don't just accept the very
first prompt it gives you. Tip number
nine, use the new branching feature. You
can actually start separating off into
different branches of your conversation.
So, let's say I don't like this
tightened up version that it made. I can
come back to the original version that
it wrote, click on these three little
dots and branch in new chat. If I click
this, it starts off the chat from here
and drops the second response that we
gave. This time I can say make it
funnier, add a bunch of jokes. And now
I've branched off a new version with our
jokes. So I can come here, see our
original script, our tightened up
100word script, and then I can click on
this second chat again, see our
original, see where it branched off
from, and then see our second funnier
script. So we can always have like a
save point that we can jump back to and
continue the chat from those save
points, which is a pretty cool new
feature that I think was much needed. If
you're working on a much bigger project,
you can actually chunk it into multiple
steps and tell chat GPT all of the steps
from the beginning, but just have it
work through one step at a time. For
example, we're writing a sponsor read
that promotes chat GPT. It should be 45
to 60 seconds, and work it in stages.
Stage one, write the brief. Stage two,
the outline, stage three, the draft, but
start with stage one only. So, from the
very beginning of this chat thread,
we're telling it all three stages we're
eventually going to get to, but we're
telling it just start with this first
stage. So, we can go ahead and submit
this. And we can see that it gave us a
quick brief. Who's the audience? What's
the promise? What's the tone? The value
hook, and then the CTA. And then it
says, "Want me to move on to stage two
outline?" I don't need to type anything
but yes, unless I had feedback on the
brief. So, let's just say yes. and then
it'll move on to stage two and write our
whole outline for us. Working through in
steps like this ensures that larger
processes sort of go more smoothly
because you're breaking them up into
smaller steps that's easier for the bot
to understand. All right, so now we've
got our intro line, our proof points,
two, and three, and then our CTA, our
call to action. Want me to move to step
three? Yes. And just like that, it wrote
the script for us. If you wanted to do
an even better job and really think
through the script, you can actually
turn on thinking modes and actually have
it think a little bit harder during each
step and probably get an even better
result. But bigger projects, you can
chunk out into multiple steps and you'll
likely get much more impressive end
results from them. You can also ask
ChatGpt to make assumptions for you and
then help correct the assumptions. So,
here's an example. I'd like to make a
marketing plan for a small coffee shop.
But first, list the assumptions you're
making about the shop budget and
location. Let's let ChatGpt tell us what
it thinks we're trying to make and then
we'll correct it and sort of steer it in
the right direction. So, it's making
assumptions about the shop, you know,
the size, what we offer, brand
positioning, assumptions about the
location, assumptions about our budget.
Now that we know how chat GPT would sort
of default assume things about this, we
can go in and correct any information
that it has incorrect in here and we're
starting off from a much better starting
point because now chat GPT is going to
better understand the exact business
we're trying to build and will be able
to much better give us a marketing plan.
So, if you're ever worried that you
didn't give enough details, ask it to
give you back any assumptions that it
currently has, and then you can close
those gaps for ChatGpt. You can also ask
ChatGpt to ask you questions to help it
better do its job. For example, I want
to start a side hustle. Ask me five
questions that will help you give me the
best possible ideas. And we get our five
questions. How many hours per week can
you dedicate? What's your budget? Do you
want to leverage existing skills? What
is your income goals? and your work
style. Do you prefer online, digital, or
something more hands-on? If I answer all
of these questions, it can start
recommending various side hustles for
me. And I don't need to give too much
detail. For time commitment, I can just
put a one and say 5 hours per week. For
budget, let's say $500 a month. I want
to leverage AI. Let's say I want to make
3K a month. And I prefer to work from
home at my computer. It knows the
context of the five questions, so I
don't need to give it much more than
that. And just like that, I've got a
bunch of side hustle ideas that fit into
the criteria that I gave it. If you want
to steal any of them and use them for
yourself, feel free to pause and look at
the screen right now. I just minimized
it so you can see it better. Tip number
13. If you're getting facts, make sure
you verify the facts because AI will
hallucinate and confidently make up
stuff and make you think that what it's
telling you is true when sometimes it
isn't. If I plug in the prompt, what are
the top three bestselling electric cars
in 2025? It should automatically search
the web, and it is. And then it found
this information for me. The Tesla Model
Y, Tesla Model 3, and the BYD Seagull,
which is interesting cuz I've never even
heard of it. But see these little links
off to the side? These are the sources.
So, if you're unsure if it got something
right, make sure you click on this
source and see if the source is actually
a good, accurate source. Because when
you're dealing with facts, again, AI
might make stuff up sometimes or pull
old information. It might pull
information from 2022 when we ask it a
question about 2025. So, definitely
double check, especially if it's going
into like a YouTube video or blog post
or a podcast or a live presentation or a
slide deck or something like that. Make
sure your facts are right cuz again, AI
will confidently mislead you from time
to time. Tip number 14, you can use
files inside of chat GPT. This is
actually one of my favorite uses of just
AI in general is taking long complex
documents and getting it to simplify
them for you. So here's an example of a
paper that OpenAI put out called why
language models hallucinate and it is a
36page report on why the models actually
hallucinate filled with math that I
can't even begin to understand myself.
But if I take this research paper, drop
it into chat GPT here, and then
accompany it with a prompt like, "Here's
a PDF of a research paper. Summarize it
into five key takeaways and cite page
numbers." It will read the document for
me and give me the five key takeaways.
Hallucinations are statistical and not
mysterious. That's mentioned on pages 1
through three and then again on pages 6
through 7. Pre-training inevitably
produces errors, tells us which page to
find that information on, etc., etc. And
you can plug any PDF document into this
and have it summarize it for you. And
then you can do things like explain this
paper like I'm five. And then it gives
you a really dumbed down version so dumb
dums like me can understand what it
actually all means. Tip number 15, use
the canvas feature inside of chat GPT.
Not familiar with the canvas feature?
Well, let's give it a prompt like create
a script for a fictional short film
about werewolves. And then under the
plus here, go down to mode and then turn
on the canvas. So it uses the canvas
feature. Now when I submit this, you'll
see that it creates this like
subdocument inside of chat GPT with our
script. This is the canvas. Once it's
done writing our script within the
canvas, we can download our script. We
can copy it or we can edit it. So if I
click edit, you can see that it moved my
chat over to the left sidebar. And now
this is an editable document. I can add
more text in here and build off of what
it created directly inside of chat GPT.
I can also let AI help with the editing
of what it already created. Down in the
bottom right, there's this little button
that if I hover over it, it gives me
extra options like suggest edits, adjust
the length, change the reading level,
add final polish, or add emojis. Let's
go ahead and change the reading level.
I'll click the reading level button, and
then there's just basically a little
slider that I can go all the way up to
graduate school, all the way down to
kindergarten. and let's go to high
school reading level. Click one more
time to submit. And watch, we will
actually see it edit in real time. We
can see this little hover as it's going
down and editing our text for us. And
now we have an edited version because
our chat on the left told us it edited
it for us. Another really cool feature
is let's say I don't really like this
chunk right here. Well, I can go to the
right and this little plus comes up and
I can edit just this right here. Let's
say make this part funny. Submit that.
And we can see I'm not touching
anything. It just edited that little
section to make it funnier. So that's
what the canvas does. It works really
good for editing text. And this is also
what you would see if you were messing
with code. It will open up the code in
canvas as well. Tip number 16. Slightly
redundant, but you can use the temporary
chat if you want to have a chat session
that it doesn't remember. I already
mentioned that. already chatted about
that, but that feature is available if
you know you want to ask about that
weird mole on your Nether region and you
don't want it saved in your chat
history. Well, you can use that for it.
You can upload images as well. If I
upload this image here of a bunch of
people that were at an event with me and
I said, "How many people are in this
image?" I can let it count for me. And
it counted 20 people in the image. I
just double checked myself and there's
19. And again, another reason why you
always want to double check its work.
Now, if I turn on thinking and ask it
again, well, it thought for 3 and 1/2
minutes and still was off by one. But
it's interesting looking through the
thinking. It was trying to do a bunch of
math and calculate the location of each
face. And somehow it managed to count 20
people both times. Again, double check
its work. For whatever reason, with math
and counting, it sometimes gets hung up.
But one thing it is good at is it can
read text on a screen really, really
well. So, I was watching a YouTube video
the other day and they actually put a
prompt on the screen. They didn't put it
in the description or anywhere you could
copy and paste the prompt. It was just
shown on the screen and I wanted to copy
and paste and test the prompt. So, I
screenshotted the YouTube video where
the prompt was shown and said, "Please
OCR this text for me and tell me what it
says." OCR stands for optical character
recognition. It's basically like a way
of looking at an image and pulling the
text from the image. That's a simplified
explanation. And you can see it just
gave me the text of the prompt back
where I can copy and paste it into
wherever I wanted. So it can understand
images but maybe can't always count the
faces. And then tip number 18 is to
actually use chat GPT to help you come
up with prompts for chat GPT. For
example, I want to build a successful
work from home business. What are some
amazing prompts that I can ask that will
help get me going in the right
direction? If I give it this, it will
give me prompts that I can then turn
around and give back to chat GPT. And we
can see here that this is how it
structures the prompts when you ask it
to write prompts for you. Given my
skills in X, what are 10 work from home
business models that are profitable in
2025? Act like a business strategist.
Help me choose a business that fits my
time commitment, income, goals,
personality. Validating demand, prompts
around that. Designing the model,
prompts around that. automating and
scaling, mindset and execution. So, it
is flatout telling you, here's how you
prompt me to get the best possible
responses. All right. Now, in the final
part of this video, I want to kind of
rapid fire some of my favorite prompts
that I think a new user of Chat GPT
should go try to really find out what
it's capable of.
[Music]
Number one, rewrite an email. Rewrite
this email to be friendly, concise, and
120 to 150 words. Keep my request and
deadline. Then give a subject line. And
then right below this, you would paste
in the email that you want rewritten so
that it has that look and feel you're
going for. Number two, summarize the
attached article in five bullets for a
non-technical reader. Include two quotes
worth sharing. We already kind of demoed
this when we looked at uploading PDFs.
Learning a topic. Explain topic to me
like I'm new to it. Then give me a five
question quiz and answer key. So for
example, the topic could be quantum
computing. Brainstorming ideas. Give 10
ideas for goal for each a one-s sentence
idea who it helps and the first step. So
example, give 10 ideas for an AI tweet
thread. Create a table out of some
information. Turn this text into a table
with columns. Task owner deadline risk.
Watch it as it creates tables like we
saw earlier in the video. Creating
outlines. Make a 10-point outline for a
five-minute talk on, let's say, AI
tools. Ask me three questions before
drafting. It'll give me three questions.
I answer the questions. It will draft an
outline for a 5-minute talk based on
that. Do an editing pass on work that
you've already written. Edit this script
for clarity and flow. Keep my tone.
Return a diff style list of changes. You
can use it to analyze data in a
spreadsheet. From the uploaded CSV, list
three insights and two follow-up
questions, then propose one chart. It
could be used for translation. Translate
to your desired language. Keeping humor
and casual tone, flag any culture
specific phrases. It could be a personal
coach. Act as a role, ask me five
diagnostic questions, then give a 7-day
plan I can follow. For example, act as a
health coach, ask me five diagnostic
questions, etc. And one that I use
constantly is comparing products against
each other. So, for example, make a
table comparing the iPhone 16 Pro and
Google Pixel 10. And this works so well
if you're trying to debate between two
different products. But that's it. That
is the complete beginners guide to using
Chat GPT. Everything that I think a new
user of this tool should know. If
there's any takeaways that I really want
you to take from this is that you should
talk to it like a person that you would
talk to on Slack or a text message. Use
projects to organize your conversations
and create specific little buckets of
memory and context so that when you're
inside of that project, it just uses the
information from within that project.
Super super helpful. And don't always
take everything chat GPT tells you as
fact. You definitely still want to
double check it because it will
hallucinate and kind of gaslight you
sometimes. But I think once you learn to
just chat with it like you're chatting
with another human over Slack or text
message, that's when it really unlocks
and it starts to feel like you're
chatting with a good friend who
understands you and your business and
can really really help you out. And it
feels more and more powerful. I was at
an event recently and I talked to
somebody who had never used ChatGpt in
their life. they've never once opened it
up and tried it and entered a single
prompt, which inspired me to make this
video. But I also wanted to make sure
that if somebody did want to use it for
the first time, they have a resource to
go and learn the best ways to use it,
what to expect, and to also help them
realize that it isn't a endall beall
super intelligence that knows
everything. It still has some flaws and
some areas that it will struggle with.
Now, if you do want to deep dive into
more advanced prompt engineering tips
and be in the top like 0.01%
of all prompt engineers and chat GPT
users, I made a video with even deeper
dives on various chat GPT prompting
techniques. You can find the video over
on my YouTube channel. It's called the
most powerful chat GPT prompts right
now. Again, that moves into much more
advanced prompting strategies and really
deep dives into how you can get the
absolute most out of chat GPT. So, check
that video out if you haven't already.
But, thank you so much for tuning into
this one. Hopefully, you learned a lot,
even if you aren't a total chat GPT
noob. Uh, I'm sure there's some tips
that you got out of this one that maybe
you hadn't thought of. And regardless,
thank you so much for spending your time
with me, nerding out with me, and
learning about ChatGpt with me. I have a
blast making these videos and I really
really appreciate everyone that watches
this channel and wants to learn from me.
I'm here to help and my goal with every
video is to be as helpful as possible.
So hopefully I accomplish that goal with
this video and hopefully you click that
like button and that subscribe button
and I'll see you in a future video.
Thanks again for tuning in. Really
appreciate you. Bye-bye. Thank you so
much for nerding out with me today. If
you like videos like this, make sure to
give it a thumbs up and subscribe to
this channel. I'll make sure more videos
like this show up in your YouTube feed.
And if you haven't already, check out
futuretools.io where I share all the
coolest AI tools and all the latest AI
news. And there's an awesome free
newsletter. Thanks again. Really
appreciate you. See you in the next one.